[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software if slow QA processes bottleneck
you or your software engineering team
and you're releasing slower because of
it you need to check out QA wolf.com QA
wolf gets engineering teams to 80%
automated end-to-end test coverage and
helps them ship two times faster by
reducing QA Cycles from hours to minutes
with over 105 star reviews on G2 and
customer testimonials from salesloft
daata AutoTrader and many more you're in
good hands go to QA wolf.com to see if
they can help you squash the QA
bottleneck for software engineering
radio this is Robert blumen today I have
with me Jim bugia Jim is the co- founder
and CEO of nurata he's an advocate for
cloud native Computing best practices he
is a chair of two working groups of the
cloud native Computing foundation
kubernetes multi-tenancy and kubernetes
policy and he's a committer on the open-
source kerno project he's a frequent
speaker at conferences such as Cloud
native security con Jim welcome to
software engineering radio thanks for
having me Robert pleasure to be here we
will be talking about polic as code in
kerno today before we get started is
there anything else about your
background that you'd like to share with
listeners sure so I'm a software
engineer still actively of course
contributing in multiple projects I
started my career in software
engineering in the telecommunication
space so building distributed systems in
a very very different manner than what
we see today so worked at you know
companies like Motorola Labs loosened
and now as you mentioned focus more on
cloud native Systems Great and that's
what we will be talking about today I
know from reading the documentation that
kerno is a policy management tool for
kubernetes we're going to get all into
that but let's start high level talking
about policies when we are talking about
these kind of policies what are we
talking about and how are these managed
policies distinct from there are a
number of things in the kubernetes space
that are also called policy right yes so
policy is quite an abstract and vague
term right but if you kind of think
about it in our real lives and our
day-to-day work we have policies for
things like expenses and vacations and
things like that which are just written
somewhere these are documents that we
share and we all want to abide by within
an organization so similarly if you
think about what's happened in it in the
last you know let's say say 10 or so
years we've moved from system
administration to devops to Dev secc Ops
so we have more and more collaboration
across different teams different groups
that's required and what that brings in
is as you're sharing configuration as
you're managing these increasingly
complex and large systems you need some
form of digital policy which everybody
is going to look at in the organization
and abide by and some of these policies
may be because of Regulatory Compliance
even across the industry like PCI Hippa
Etc which are in financial systems in
health care or they might be internal
best practices which are set up but then
again in this form of policy we're
really talking about a digital artifact
which all different collaborators can
look at can understand what that means
and know exactly how to apply that
within their domains itself might help
if we could get more specific I noticed
in the documentation site for kerno
there's a section which lists perhaps
several dozen categories of policies
what are some of the categories of
policies that are managed by kerno yeah
great question right so kerno started
life in kubernetes you know within the
cncf and as you may know you know within
kubernetes the the unit of deployment
and management of any workload is a pod
so incubates also you know all
configuration is very declarative so you
tell the system how you would like it to
behave and then various controllers go
off and do their job and try to bring
the current state of the system to the
desired state so starting with that
context if you kind of go back to every
workload and developers want to specify
the configuration for their workload
they would write you know several
different things for in and kubernetes
declarations are in yaml format so they
would write things about how many
replicas their pod might have what types
of resources their pod has which
container images the Pod needs to run so
all of that gets specified in a pod
declaration but then the Pod declaration
also has things like a security context
which every container you know there's
certain security rules or security
configuration you want to attach it may
have things like a note selector so
again you're within that same
declaration within that single yaml
artifact there's things that the
developer cares about there's things
that the opst team cares about and
there's things that the security team
cares about so a very concrete example
of a policy for security is within that
pod to make sure that the security
context abides by certain rules rules
for Best Practices to make sure there
can be no container breakouts or
privilege escalations things like that
for a workload so that's something a
security team can Define as a policy in
cerno and can deploy that across all
their clusters kerno operates as an
admission controller so anytime there's
a change request within a cluster kerno
can intercept that request understand
what that change means and apply the set
of policy is required to either allow or
deny that request so you just gave us
one example of the workload permission
could you give another example of a
policy that I could download or viiew on
the kyero website absolutely so one
extremely simple and common example is
you know you want to make sure that
every workload has certain labels right
and labels are used for best practices
for organizing data for querying things
like that so ensuring that your
organizational labels are set like the
team you know ID or something that
correlates who ordered that workload or
who's requesting or running it because
kubernetes and Cloud native environments
tend to be shared so you have
heterogeneous multiple workloads working
on common infrastructure so things like
labeling becomes that's a simple policy
another example would be like every time
a new name space is created in
kubernetes to auto automatically
generate some secure defaults like for
networking you know the firewall rules
what traffic is allowed in and out off
that workload those sort of things you
could also generate by default security
related tools we could perhaps classify
them into these two groups which do
scans and give you a report of things
you need to fix and other things that
are active at real time that will block
you from doing anything you must not do
and it will allow you to do things that
you may do can you easily put kerno into
one or the other group or does it have
elements of both it does do both but the
main value there is that proactive
enforcement because there are like you
mentioned there's several scanning tools
which can react to configuration that's
already in production but by the time
something's in production it's too late
so what you want to do is you want to
prevent invalid configurations from
going to production if you look at all
the security headlines you know the
common results are about 80 to 90% of
security issues are because of
misconfigurations and the real value
proposition of a tool like cerno is
preventing
misconfigurations as early as possible
in your software development life cycle
and we've all heard about shift left in
security with cerno we think of it as
shift down security because we're baking
this into the platform itself we're
going to get more a little bit later
into some other things you've mentioned
like the controllers and how the
policies are written I want to stay for
a minute at this high level you
mentioned that many organizations are
driven to adopt policies in order to
comply with different standards like s
so you have hundreds of policies
pre-written on covero website to what
extent do you have compliance in a box
type solution where you could download
50 or 100 policies as a package that
would get you some percentage of the way
toward a given type of compliance for
kubernetes you know best practices or
security related configuration kerno has
a very solid and strong policy set out
of the box you can just get started with
and that's because the kubernetes
community also maintains something
called pod security standards which is a
you know live document which evolves
with every release and cerno policies
offer that now if you move higher to
standards like whether it's PCI DSS
Hippa you know those type of things
there's vendor tooling like from you
know my company n Mar other companies
like rat and also like other Cloud
providers that would provide these
compliance standards built on cerno
policies or other policy engines
as a complete solution the challenge
that we saw with kerno and what we
wanted to address is and we often kind
of face this during the audit process
right every environment with kubernetes
because there's so much extensibility
different environments might have
different sets of tools so to prove
compliance requires that flexibility in
policies like one you know maybe one
environment uses esto as a service mesh
another uses linkerd and each one may
have different set of best practices so
that's where having the ability to
easily in a declarative manner manage
this policy life cycle as policy as code
becomes extremely important when we're
talking about now the management of
policies one example would be allow and
deny I understand Governor can also
modify requests before they're applied
to correct them can you give an example
of when you would do that absolutely yes
so one simple example is if you're
deploying a workload and if it doesn't
contain any resource request now
anything that you want to run on your
cluster will consume some CPU some
memory and perhaps some other resources
like gpus Etc so it makes sense to have
some baseline of requests because
otherwise what happens is the workload
kubernetes schedules it as best effort
which means that if there's some other
workload comes in and requests resources
the best effort workload may get you
know descheduled or may get moved out of
the certain nodes so to prevent that
it's important that any application that
you expect to keep running longlived
applications have resource requests so
for something like this you know
developers may not know the what to set
so administrators can set a default CPU
minimum as well a default memory minimum
and with autotuning in kubernetes it's
possible to then adjust this based on
heuristics and observability metrics
that are collected over time in your
example then the modification would be
if a request for workload does not have
resource constraints attached then kyera
would apply a reasonable default to that
request absolutely and it can tune that
over time too right which is quite
interesting because based on
in kubernetes environments typically
you're collecting metrics you have
things in Prometheus as a metric server
so cerno can integrate with the metric
server check for resource consumption
and tune that because the newer versions
of kubernetes now support vertical pod
Auto scalers which allow in place
updates to some of these metrics you did
start out to tell us the history of the
project we got partway down that road I
I wonder if do you have an awareness of
how standard is either kerna or policy
management in general as one of the
services that pretty much every cluster
needs to run or where are we on that
adoption curve for the concept of policy
management cncf runs surveys on some of
this and especially on their top
projects to see and measure adoption so
from the latest surveys what we have
seen is about 40% right now of the
respondents are using some form of
policy management kerno has about you
know like about half of that share the
other half is with another tool called
open policy agent which uses Rego as a
policy language so that's another you
know solution in the cncf landscape for
policy management but to your question
and what is a good point is there's
still work to be done in terms of
awareness that policy is really a must
have for systems like kubernetes and you
need some form of policy enforcement
whether you're using cerno or
Alternatives in the community if I'm
adopting caverno I'm of course going to
look through what policies people have
already written but then I may find
nobody's written the policy that I want
I wanted first to ask can these
pre-built policies be parameterized or
can they indirectly import settings from
your cluster so that you can to some
extent customize them the way you want
yes so cernal policies you can declare
variables and you can pull this variable
data from external sources whether it's
config maps in your cluster other
controllers you can even cache these
periodically in a global cache that
kerno offers so there's a lot of
flexibility in parameterizing
externalizing data which may vary over
time like in the metric example right so
if you're checking with the metric
server if that metric server happens to
be in cluster you know that's fairly low
latency you can make some rapid calls to
it and check but if you are doing that
check with something off cluster you
might want to periodically pull down
that data cach it into your cluster and
then make a decision of whether to
mutate or whether to allow or deny
workloads like that can you think of a
situation either you encountered or
maybe a user where they looked through
the pre-built policies they couldn't
find it and they had to write their own
policy absolutely right so we do see and
one of the again motivations for
introducing kerno so kerno started about
two years after open policy agent and
what we noticed is as much as you know
the community understood the use cases
for open policy agent adoption stayed
fairly low because of the complexity of
writing policies in Rego being a
different language being something which
was a learning curve for kubernetes
admins so when we started kuo one of the
guidelines for the project was we want
anybody who learns kubernetes to be able
to write gno policies without any
additional training or knowledge or
without any language to learn so
starting out with kerno is extremely
simple literally you can go from zero to
you know value in under five minutes and
then as you want to customize or write
more complex policies kerno does allow
you know languages like James path or
cell which is a newer language which a
lot of kubernetes controllers and
kubernetes itself is starting to you
know adopt cell stands for common
Expressions language so it's another way
of you know kind of declaring small
pieces of logic or code within things
like configuration like yaml
configurations so yes so it's very
common for folks to customize our right
policies we also see a lot of questions
on our community channels kerno has a
very active slack channel in the
kubernetes workspace in fact we are
ranked like the second most active right
after kubernetes itself which is
interesting as a statistic and we see a
lot of questions on help with policies
things like that as kubernetes ad
administrators are customizing these
policies to their needs now looking at
these policies You' mentioned they are
written in yml but it looked to me like
some of it was very declarative and some
of it was a little bit imperative in
that it was importing looping type
Concepts and so could you comment more
on what is involved in implementing a
policy what type of languages or
libraries do you need to master yeah so
the first thing is of course standing
kubernetes itself right so most policies
or I would say the simpler policies you
know which like the bulk of the 60 50
60% of policies are fairly
straightforward they will mimic the
structure of the resource that you're
trying to apply the policy to so for
example if you're applying a policy to a
pod and pods have things like spec and
every kubernetes declaration you know
the sort of the de facto way of
declaring it it has a spec element and a
status element spec of course is short
for specification and within that you
would have things like you know with for
a pod you would have containers within a
container you would have security
contexts so that's how the you know yaml
is laid out so a policy to match
something in a security context would
follow almost exactly that same
structure so it becomes extremely simple
for somebody who understands how a pod
declaration
looks like to be able to write a CNO
policy that matches that structure and
enforces some constraints on certain
Fields within the pot so that's you know
very easy straightforward starting point
but then there's things like you
mentioned in a kuity SP you could have
multiple containers and containers are
organized as either a container
declaration which is the main you know
your application container or you could
have init containers you can even have
ephemeral containers which is a newer
feature so now you know if you want to
really enforce some security constraint
you might need to Loop across all
Container types and all containers
within each of those types and enforce
some policy so that's where you know
cerno has things like for each as a
declaration or has ways to apply there's
another language called James path which
is an acronym jmes path it's commonly
used for CIS and to process Json in an
efficient you know time bound manner so
kerno supports that language common
Expressions language or cell is also
something that Kera 110 onwards has
added support for and common expression
languag is used in kubernetes in in a
few different places so there are as you
get to more complicated policies you
will end up using either James path or
cell or in some cases both depending on
what you want to accomplish if I want to
constrain values like something must be
greater than zero I can see that's
completely declarative but I can imagine
situations where I have or I need to
write a service in a high Lev language
and the rule I'm trying to express is
call this service and it will tell you
whether you can do the thing or not so
I've essentially factored out a portion
of my policy into another program that
may be imperative is it possible to
integrate that type of logic into a
policy yes so CNO supports API calls to
either internal kubernetes services with
you know bir directional security with
other checks so you can call any other
kubes controller or you can even call an
external API the only caution there is
if you're calling external apis
especially if your policy is applying
during admission controls you need to
make sure that it executes extremely
efficiently and there's low latency in
those calls because you're blocking you
know any other API calls while that's
occurring I noticed on the kerno
documentation page and discussed this a
little while ago there are categories
and in within each category there are
many policies does kerno have any
concept like package management where I
can say I want all the cncf node
policies as a bundle and then it will go
and grab at a larger granularity there
is a way to organize so cerno itself
doesn't do this but there's higher level
Tools in kubernetes in the ecosystem and
of course other tools that build on
cerno but very commonly you will see you
know the term policy sets which like
you're envisioning is a bundle it's a
group of related policies that you want
deploy and operate together so one
common packaging for anything in
kubernetes is Helm charts right so cerno
policies because they're kubernetes
resources can be easily organized into a
Helm chart you can deploy that as a
versioned unit you can even put you know
with tools like flux and Argo CD you can
put that Helm chart into an oci registry
and pull it down into your cluster so
the beauty of kerno is because you know
the approach is to that POC IES are just
kubernetes resources you use the tooling
you would normally use for other
kubernetes resources to manage policy as
code and that life cycle as well so you
don't need any custom tools which other
you know engines or other Solutions
require you to use them got it so
kubernetes already has a package manager
which is Helm you don't need to provide
a new package manager for kerno because
you use the one that everybody's
okay great this last response you gave
does start to get into another thing I
want to cover which is how do you get
kyero bootstrapped into your cluster
clearly I would like as much as possible
of all the things I'm running to be
compliant with policies but you have to
get certain amount of stuff set up
before you could even install kyno so
can you take us through where in the
cluster standup does kerno fit yes so
kubernetes has a concept of a control
plane and then a data plane which are
the worker nodes attached to the control
plane right and the control plane runs
things like edcd the API server other
kubernetes controllers like the
scheduler Etc so the of course when
you're provisioning a cluster the
control plane components come up first
and those typically run if you're
running an ha configuration the minimum
you know recommended is three for
consensus across availability zones or
for raft consensus also for ETD so
typically you bring up your API server
first the other thing that kubernetes
clusters will require and worker nodes
do not go into uh running or available
State until you have a cni installed
right and a cni is the container
networking interface in kubes so you
would usually install projects like
either celium or Calico or one of of
those as your cni and then cerno tends
to be the next thing you want to get
installed before anything else is
allowed right so the order would be
control plane components cni for
networking because if you don't run your
cni worker nodes are not available and
kerno installs as a deployment on the
worker nodes so you do need to make sure
that's up and running first and then
cerno and then all of the other
controllers you want to bring in cuz
policies need to apply to controllers as
well like Prometheus needs to be secured
or ISO needs to be secured so you want
to make sure that kerno comes right
after the cni but and before everything
else all the other base controllers and
then of course workloads which app teams
would then deploy subsequently on the
cluster I want to refer our listeners to
episode 590 on standing up a cluster and
episode 619 on the kubernetes NW working
or we cover the cni so now back to kerno
you said it installs as a deployment is
there one or more Helm charts for kyero
it's a single Helm chart and within that
Helm chart though there's multiple
controllers custom resources so it's a
fairly you know full featured Helm chart
which installs a number of things on the
cluster cerno itself runs as you know
four different controllers so there's an
admission controller which receives
requests directly from the API server
there's a cleanup controller which runs
you know for cleanup resources there's a
reporting controller which is
responsible for reporting and then
there's a background controller which
can apply mutate and generate rules to
existing workloads within your cluster
so those are the four controllers for
deployments which will bring you will
see within the cerno namespace itself
but it's a single Helm chart which you
can you know install again using any
standard tools or gitops tools like Argo
CD flux and others you mentioned then it
does have its own its own name space yes
if I listed objects in the Nam space and
forgive you if you don't have 100% of
this on top of mine but what are some or
most of the resources you would see in
the name space when it's running yes so
in kubes nam spaces are the sort of
security boundary and unit of isolation
so the best practice is to use a
separate name space for each workload so
cerno installs in its own namespace in
there you would see these four
deployments that I mentioned and of
course based on your ha configuration
you might see multiple pods for these
and you will see things like you know
CNO will self-generate like a
certificate which it uses to register
with the API server you might see other
resources so there will be a secret for
that and that creates some other cluster
wide resources internally but all of
this is fully automated right and few
other things you'll see like you'll see
a kerno config map which is used for
certain parameters to configure kerno
things like that within that namespace
is kyero a state full service no it's
stateless and the way it works you know
there's different I guess High
availability modes based on which
controller you're kind of focused on or
looking at for the admission controller
it's completely stateless and it scales
out which means you can grow the number
of replicas to handle a higher load you
can of course scale each admission
controller up as well other controllers
like the background controller or the
report controller will run leader
elections for certain tasks which means
that only one of them will be elected
the leader within their cluster of
services and will be performing a task
but if that you know leader goes down
there's a immediate reelection which
automatically happens and a new instance
is you know elected as the leader and it
will take over those tasks can you say a
bit more about why would it be important
for a tool that is examining requests
and accepting or denying to have a
leader so there are certain things like
say for example I mentioned that kerno
automatically generates a secret and a
certificate to register securely with
the API server right and it periodically
checks whether that certificate needs to
be regenerated has expired Etc now you
don't want all instances of cerno to be
constantly checking that so tasks like
those are you know delegated to one
leader instance but of course it's all
stateless in the sense that so it's
stateful at that moment in time but if
that leader goes down for even a few
milliseconds another new leader will be
immediately elected and that takes over
that task you've mentioned a couple of
times the admission controller I'm aware
from the documentation that it is a
instance of a kubernetes object called a
dynamic admission controller and that's
not specific to kerno could you review
what that controller is in general for
kubernetes and then we'll come back to
kerno sure so Dynamic admission
controllers are a way of extending
kubernetes you know kubernetes has a
concept called custom resource
definitions which is extremely powerful
right so you can you you can extend the
API and have your own object
declarations in open API V3 schema
Dynamic admission controllers you know
along that theme of extensibility what
they allow you to do is after any API
request is so all API requests go to the
API server anytime the API request hits
the API server it's first authenticated
and authorized and after that phase of
processing there's another phase called
admission controls kubernetes has
built-in admission controls which are
part of the API server so you can toggle
these using Flags using arguments when
you configure the API server if you're
running your own kubernetes if you're
using a cloud provider or manage KU
ities you have to go through their
configuration to toggle these but then
there's you know after the built-in
admission control is applied then
kubernetes applies Dynamic admission
controls which is a call out to any
external service or deployment which can
also get an admission request from the
API server and can you know participate
in either allowing or denying that
requests based on the payload and based
on other configurations so cerno like
you mentioned
is an example of a dynamic admission
controller it runs as its own workload
outside of the API server and then gets
these requests so Dynamic admission
controllers much like with anything in
software there's always trade-offs right
so they can if they're not configured
correctly or if they end up taking too
much latency there could be challenges
in scaling and managing the cluster
correctly so they have to be extremely
performant
very fast typically milliseconds in
terms of you know responding so cerno is
highly tuned highly optimized for that
type of workload where it will cash
everything in memory make admission
decisions very quickly but it is
possible to write policies in a manner
like we were chatting about earlier
where if you end up making external API
calls you end up injecting latency right
but going back to Dynamic admission
controllers it's an external service
which the API server will call out to
and delegate an admission decision to
say should I allow this API request to
proceed or should I prevent it and you
know with some reason for why it was
blocked so the word in this case
admission it's maybe a little bit quirky
but that means in effect an API call to
the kubernetes API is that right that's
correct and every change in kubernetes
anytime you change any configuration
even if you generate an event in
kubernetes it goes through the same
process goes through the API server it
delegates goes through all of these
phases even if you're trying to exact
into a pod or mount a file all of that
is subject to the same process and how
are these Dynamic emmission controllers
authorized great question right so
kubernetes has something called token
review which is built in into it right
so from a security perspective you can
use token review to know that this
request is coming from a trusted Source
you can of course when you're you know
configuring these admission controllers
you can also set up standard rback and
this is where putting them in a
namespace which is secured is extremely
important so what you want to avoid and
kerno by default avoids this is policies
are not applied to the kerno Nam space
itself right and that obviously you know
can be a security risk if the kuo
namespace is not properly secured so it
becomes like a bootstrapping problem
again where you need that first rout of
trust you need to make sure that every
layer is properly secured but then as
you're getting API requests kerno can
check and see that that request came
from the proper source and of course
when kerno registers so it registers
itself using something called Web hook
configuration so there's a validating
web hook configuration and a mutating
webbook configuration and the secret
that I mentioned that kerno manages you
could bring your own certificates but if
you don't kerno will itself generate a
certificate and that's how the API
server knows that kerno is trusted for
admission requests as well so what level
of authorization is needed to run the
helm chart that installs kyero you have
to be an administrator right so you
can't be just a normal user so these are
cluster much like with again again a cni
or other kind of controllers a cluster
admin would need to install this so you
do need permissions to create custom
resources within your cluster you need
permissions to change things like webook
configurations which impact
significantly the cluster behaviors
right so only admins can do this I'm
building a cluster I booted up then just
like you said I install kerno as the
next thing after the control plane and
the cni at what point do you install the
policies that kyero is enforcing so that
is right after you bring up cerno the
next thing you would want to do is roll
out the policies usually if you're using
something like you know Argo CD or flux
that would be the next workload so you
first want to make sure cerno itself is
up and ready and these tools will check
and make sure the status of these
controllers says there healthy and when
kerno responds as healthy you can start
deploying policies so you would do that
as the next you know workload right
after CNO we've gone through these steps
added some more workload that we want to
run on kubernetes and later on down the
road we want to
upgrade just policies but not
necessarily kerno itself could you talk
about upgrading policies and are
policies themselves versioned so that
it's clear what version of Any Given
policy I have running yes so you would
want to version and and again we think
of this as policy as code so much like
you would with a software application or
any other code you're deploying you want
to manage your policies in git or some
other version controlled system you want
to bundle them using package managers
like Helm and you want to you know
deploy them either again through gitops
or through oci Registries so all of
those best practices and of course you
know you you want to unit test as well
as endtoend test those policies before
they hit your production clusters right
so all of that is extremely important
but then the basic unit of you know
anything being as code is to build in
that versioning and you typically rather
than versioning each individual policy
you would want to version them as a
policy set so and package that policy
set as a Helm chart or some git repo
which then a gitops controller will
deploy now once you have kyero running
there is another type of failure mode or
error that the kubernetes developers can
encounter which is the thing they want
to do has been denied because it
violates a policy what kind of feedback
error messages logs or how does a
developer become aware that they have
been denied access because they violated
a policy which policy what exactly in
the policy failed so several options
here and depending on the type of
cluster the environment and how you want
to and then even the organization you
can decide which one to use one is of
course if the workload is blocked at
admission controls then you know there's
immediate feedback based on the
deployment tool you're using using like
again a giops controller or if you're
just using CU cuddle this kubernetes CLI
you will see that you know the error or
the reason why it was blocked directly
in the CLI and all of this is
customizable within the policy right so
as you're authoring policies you can
customize that message you can even link
to your internal like wiki page or
knowledge base on Remediation in fact
you know Solutions like nurata which
build on top of given know give
customizable remediation help and
guidance all of that you know built in
you know so that's one one way is just
you're enforcing and blocking now for
workloads which are already deployed
because imagine you already have a
production cluster you're adopting cerno
and now you're rolling out policies you
want to give feedback to the existing
workload owners as well so cerno beyond
admission controls will run routine
background scans on every every workload
will apply you know the policies and
that data is collected in another
resource in kubernetes which is a policy
report so it shows and this is very
useful for compliance as well because
you can tell what workloads passed what
they failed and it gives you an accurate
information of all the policies that
were applied to the workload and the
violations that you know were produced
as well as which workloads are compliant
so now higher level tool can again
collect that periodically across all
your clusters can aggregate that and
show these in dashboards or you can kind
of build your own dashboards or if
you're using a just you know one or a
smaller environment with a few clusters
you can use CP cuddle and kubernetes
apis for this but that policy report one
interesting thing is it's not just
limited to kerno because what we did is
we spun out that policy report and as
you mentioned you know I co-chair in the
policy working group kuties so what we
were looking at is what can we
standardize across different policy
engines and scanners and various tools
for security and operations and
compliance and one idea was why not
standardize on the reporting format so
anything that wants to report anything
of interest in kubernetes you can use
this policy report format to report that
and kerno does the same and in fact
there's a sub project within kerno
called policy reporter which can take
things you know from cerno as well as
other scanners like it integrates with
trivy for vulnerability scanning it
integrates with Falco for runtime and it
will show you all of these reports in
that standard format across all of these
tools for your cluster if you are
developing on kubernetes and you have a
good understanding of what some of the
policies are of course you're not going
to
intentionally design service that will
violate policies but can you think of an
experience you had or some you're aware
of where they tried to do something and
it was blocked and it wasn't what they
were expecting and they learned
something a little bit unexpected about
the policies that were were running
kubernetes is is of course constantly
evolving right and there's always
interesting things happening within the
space within the ecosystem a lot of this
also depends on what you install within
kubernetes as other controllers like
well whether it's for service mesh or if
you're running Argo City
incubes you know you might need policies
for that so the interesting thing about
the community is there's always new
policies flowing in there's always new
findings like just recently you know
there was a something published by the
security company viz where they talked
about you know exploit that they
published and they documented where they
were able to use ISO to be able to you
know take advantage of another setting a
configuration setting in a kubet spot
which allows a pod one container to
share you know the network name space of
another container and then what they
were able to do is configure their role
to match the iso container role and then
they suddenly got visibility into
everything that ISO can see so things
like that which are you know again this
is a new finding you can very easily
craft a cal policy for and if you deploy
it on your clusters now of course you
you know if some unless somebody is
maliciously using this exploit you would
not expect anybody to be running as the
iso user within a regular container but
things like that would be in that
category of new findings other things
are you know kubernetes as popular as it
is it's a very large you know surface
area for a system right so not everybody
knows everything and as a developer look
I might understand how to build a Docker
or a container image or a podman image
but beyond that I don't know about all
these settings like even why should I
care what a security context is right so
unless somebody explains this to me so
as we see developers in their kubernetes
Journey there are constantly these type
of learning so say oh okay you know
maybe I have this you know share process
name space and I need to set this
default
and somebody needs to explain why does
this need to be false and or why is it
not why is it not set by default so with
kerno one other interesting thing you
could do is the security and op team can
set it to faults by default so for a
secure default and then the workload
owner if they happen to set it to true
for whatever reason it their workload
would be denied but they can configure
they can create another CNO resource
called the policy exception so they can
say I need that exception and here's why
and then the security team can sign off
on it and I mean like literally sign off
using a digital signature right they can
approve it and then that workload is
allowed so you could kind of automate
that whole workflow in a manner which is
you know conducive to devops best
practices as well as doesn't block
developers and keeps them informed every
step of the way glad you mentioned that
because I was going to ask about except
but I'll consider that matter to be
addressed now this is not specifically a
CNO question but I'm aware of a common
thing that happens where you run a
security tool and you get a report back
which contains thousands of violations
people feel totally deflated they look
at that so there's no way given our
workload and amount of people we have
we're ever going to address this and so
nothing gets done so my question is are
you Ware of groups you've seen who have
deployed kerno they gotten this report
and they've burned it down to zero and
then kept it green yes so there are it's
few but they do exist and it is possible
Right it it is it takes work it takes
effort and the you know again the power
of cerno and how it's structured in
kubernetes along with some of the other
tooling the flexible reporting the
exceptions is that you know a lot of the
problem we see with that thousands of
finding is if those findings are only
visible to a few people like the
security team in a security tool which
is only accessible to them it's not
going to help the rest of the
organization right so you really want to
democratize this and bring it into tools
that developers can see as early as
possible in their you know application
life cycle and and the platform teams
can see so multiple roles can see and
kubernetes in many ways the power of
kubernetes is its
standardization as an API you know set
right so in kubernetes is the first time
in our industry I believe that we have a
common standard for describing workloads
operating workloads and collecting
information about workloads through this
API standard and it's because it's
extensible and it's brilliantly designed
design to be extensible at scale and now
we can do that with reporting so the the
you know the way to solve this and the
way we've seen team solve this is by
applying the you know kind of adage of
divide and conquer you can't have one
team be responsible for all of this
right every security is a shared
responsibility you need to make sure
that workload owners are aware of the
best practices and as a developer if
somebody's blocking my workload I want
to know why right so give me the right
information in my tool without me having
to jump through hoops or you know
without like reactive security would be
somebody sees thousands of findings
after something's in production and now
you know there's no easy way to deal
with this as an
organization we have a episode in our
upcoming that not published by the time
this one on the process of produ ction
Readiness I could see that being policy
compliant should be incorporated into
organizations's definition of production
Readiness what's your view on that
that's absolutely correct right and and
what's very interesting and as youve
probably seen this trend within the
community especially in the cloud native
Community is this trend from devops to
devs Ops to now platform engineering
right and if you think about what
platform engineering is all about is
treating you know the platform and these
platforms are typically built on
kubernetes as a end product itself and
then offering what's known as golden
paths to developers so the idea is to
get to make you know sort of codify what
it takes to get to production Readiness
and make that very visible or make folks
very aware as early as possible so like
with kerno policies not only do they
apply as admission controls and as
background scans in clusters you can
apply this in your CI pipeline right so
you can scan kues manifest even before
they are deployed to any cluster get the
results and make developers aware to say
hey here's the best practices we as an
organizations require your's the policy
compliance we require so these are
things and you can you know show them
the remediations and of course again
higher level Solutions like nirmata does
this across you know clusters pipelines
and even cloud services because cerno it
started in kubernetes but expanded
Beyond kubernetes and can now scan any
Json or any kind of workload regardless
of where it's running I now realize I
wish i' ask you this a little bit a
while back when we were talking about
bootstrapping but AIS now you can make
up some numbers for the purpose of this
example but pick your cluster size how
much resources does kyno Need for its
services to run for some size cluster
that you'll
describe yes so typically you know what
we've seen and clusters vary a lot
across organizations right we've worked
with some customers which have you know
huge clusters with like over 5,000 nodes
others which who have hundreds of
clusters but each cluster is like 10 to
20 nodes right what matters to KERO
though is how much ity is in those
clusters because if you think about it
once a resource is configured it's
configured it's static yes there's some
overhead for background scanning but the
pressure during admission controls is
how many admission requests per second
you are getting right so the way we kind
of measure CNO scalability is through
that unit Arps admission request per
second and typically you know we have
size given no so we are in the process
of putting in a horizontal pod Auto
scale ER to for the admission controller
and that's a best practice to follow for
production but it's usually you know it
starts at around I think about 5200 Megs
you know is more than sufficient so
memory is not the constraint it's CPU
bound because processing large Json
payloads takes CPU right so kerno is
tends to be more CPU bound so typically
if you're running in any production
workload we would say about 100 Meg in
terms of memory running three instances
100 Meg each and then you know having at
least two CPUs per or you know so
allocated for instance and then with
some scaling right so you could start
much lower but then allowing it an upper
bound off that is a good size for like a
midsize production workload would be
more than sufficient I wanted to talk
about the observability of the kerno
itself does it integrate with all the
stand of whatever you might be using for
logging metrics traces and anything else
open Telemetry is the standard for cloud
native workloads so yes cerno fully
supports open Telemetry for metrics for
logging for tracing even for spans right
so you can see exactly how much time is
spent between the API server and kerno
and then Kono and any other services
you're you know calling one commonly
called you know it Services the a oci
registry which is used not just for
images but also artifacts like
signatures to say is your image signed
is was it signed by the correct cicd
workflow like your correct GitHub
workflow are there attestations like a
scan report and sbom other things
attached to your images so all of that
you can check with policies but those
require calls to the oci registry which
does introduce some potential latency in
the overall admission process but yes
open Telemetry is integrated into when
you deploy kyno with a home chart does
that come with any dashboards not by
itself right so you can there's a sub
project called policy repor which you
can install uh separately and that gives
you some in-cluster dashboards there is
a grafana dashboard which is another sub
project so if you're running tools like
grafana and Prometheus you can which
most Cloud native deployments will do
you can install that dashboard and get
some cerno metrics but cerno itself
reports the metrics and and is enabled
for it but doesn't come with dashboards
with the basic Helm chart itself if you
are set out to build a dashboard what
are one or two or three metrics that you
really want to see if you're going to
look at One dashboard it's all of the
basics of kubernetes best practice
monitoring right so the your podal your
deployment Health a number of replicas
all of that is extremely essential right
and that applies to any critical
workload including kerno but in addition
I would measure like the admission
request per second and the policy rule
execution latencies which kerno is
instrumented to report because what you
want to make sure is that no rule is
taking more than at the maximum it
should be a few seconds ideally it's you
know under you know like about 100 to
200 milliseconds in terms of execution
time great now you mentioned earlier
there's at least one other tool in this
space the open policy agent which is
uses a different language to configure
the policies are there any other key
points of comparison between kerno and
open policy agent yes so there were
different philosophies different
approaches so myself like I mentioned I
come from a operations background more
than a security background right so as
well as you know a lot of my team at
nart and then of of course as we grew
the project and built the project so
interestingly kerno was first developed
as a component in nmat wasn't called
kerno at that time and then we spun it
out as an open source you know project
so as we built cerno our Focus was
operations as well as security right so
SEC Ops rather than just purely security
so the approach we took is kerno you
know from the very beginning was
designed not just to validate enforce
and block invalid configurations or
insecure configurations but also to
mutate and generate configurations right
so which we believe is extremely
important and critical to really do end
to end and and proper policy management
so generating secure defaults in real
time in cluster is essential for
kubernetes like the the namespace
example I gave earlier anytime you
create a new namespace for whatever
reason you want to generate you know
things like fine grain roles role
bindings Network policies quotas other
you know artifacts if you're using you
know ISO maybe an ISO policy or some
other cni policy all of that needs to be
automatically generated things like if
you're deploying a workload you might
want to generate a vpa recommender
configuration to observe that workload
and fine-tune the resources for it right
so that was one of the key features in
cerno which is extremely unique to it
and then things like you know reporting
through crds Uh custom resources which
become part of the kubernetes API
exception management through the kuer
API all of those are major
differentiators in kerno you mentioned a
couple of times kerno it is an open-
source project what else are you doing
at nimada besides you contributing quite
a lot to the kerno project yeah so lots
of interesting things and open source of
course is is a lot of fun it's very
exciting to work with the community and
there's this you know sort of symbiotic
relationship between open source
projects as well as the companies that
back the open source project and then
sponsor them so for us the approach we
took is we want kerno to be very full
featured very complete and something
that you know gives almost instant value
to end users right so that's extremely
important to us and we don't intend to
cerno in any manner just to kind
of offer commercial Solutions which
unlock you know critical things for
production that's not the approach we
took instead the way we think about it
and the analogy that myself and my
co-founders at neata often use we think
of you know what nmat is to kerno as
what something like iub or gitlab is to
git so all developers understand git
commands it's not very hard it's
actually pretty easy for any
organization to run their own git server
you can run it as a Helm chart or as a
pod or things EX in a very simple manner
but the value tools like gitlab or
GitHub provide is to be allowing you
know teams to collaborate on top of git
is to provide things like audit trails
and other you know information so if you
want teams to really leverage policy as
code We Believe nurata becomes essential
much like you know a GitHub becomes
essential for a git implementation and
you know again Beyond like these Deb so
what nurata provides is collaboration
workflows developers can you know see
remediations which are you know
instrumented by your security teams
security teams can see reports the Ops
teams can manage of course policy
deployments so all of that becomes that
hub for polics code across your Fleet of
clusters for reporting and collection
whereas each cluster you can get these
reports to cuetes apis nirmata does the
D duplication the aggregation the
enrichment assignment again to the right
owners it's a lot of value there even
just from the reporting perspective and
then finally you know if kerno is
managing your policies and enforcing
these policies across your pipelines and
clusters how do you know kerno actually
is running and somebody hasn't you know
misconfigured it right so nmat also
manages that across your Fleet both
pipelines clusters and other services to
make sure that policies haven't been
tampered with the right versions of
policies are deployed on each clusters
and then in addition you also get
compliance standards so going back to
what we talked about if you want PCI
compliance or Hippa compliance or you
have your own custom standard nirmata
provides that across your Fleet of
clusters and workloads Jim I think we've
had a very good coverage of policy's
code and kerno if listeners would like
to find or follow you is there anywhere
you'd like to direct them sure I'm
pretty easy to find on most social media
sites LinkedIn as well as you know X or
Twitter of course if you're in the cncf
communities I hang out in some of the
various working groups as well as the
cerno slack channel in the kubernetes
workspace as as well as the cncf work
space Jim thank you for speaking to
software engineering radio thanks for
having me Robert my pleasure and this
has Ben Robert bluman and thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening